<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Jaidev&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Jaidev&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 May 2024 18:09:52 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jaidevd.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Essays of Revolt - Jack London </title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/essays-of-revolt-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2024 18:09:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/essays-of-revolt-review/</guid>
      <description>My company uses an e-HRM system. The system is why my colleagues and I never forget to wish each other on birthdays and anniversaries. Systems like these save us from the embarrassment of appearing indifferent. Other systems like smartphones ensure that the most halfhearted birthday greeting appears sincere and colourful. All you have to do is type “Happy” and the autocomplete does the rest - it composes the shortest message needed to show how much you care.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Great Arc - John Keay</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/the-great-arc-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/the-great-arc-review/</guid>
      <description>This book invokes two very different reactions in me. The primary reaction is jubilant, almost romantic. The second is gloomy. Imagine you’re watching Oppenheimer: spirits rising until the point the bombs actually drop, after which you feel guilty about having felt good in the first place.
The Great Trigonometric Survey was completed over the duration of a better part of a century, across three generations of mathematicians, physicists and surveyors (they were called compasswallahs - I finally see where Rohit Gupta gets his pseudonym), and at the cost of thousands of lives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: A Room of One&#39;s Own - Virginia Woolf</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/room-of-ones-own-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/room-of-ones-own-review/</guid>
      <description>I went into this essay expecting Virginia Woolf had written about what the eponymous room is like - its design and contents. But she deals with a more fundamental issue - that one needs a room of one&amp;rsquo;s own.
The essays are a fine piece of scholarship. I&amp;rsquo;d never have thought that Woolf&amp;rsquo;s characteristic device, the &amp;ldquo;stream of consciousness&amp;rdquo; could be used to not only as a writing technique, but also as a powerful pedagogical technique.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open World Games and the Myth of Sisyphus</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/myth-of-sisyphus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2022 10:04:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/myth-of-sisyphus/</guid>
      <description>To the memory of Kevin Conroy. There was only ever one true Batman.
 You have been playing for months. Slowly and steadily, you have harvested every collectable - making yourself stronger and stronger until you can kill the toughest enemies. Every enemy defeated, every monster slain. No side quest worth doing remains. Those not worth doing are also done because you are a completionist (which is a dignified way of saying that you have no life).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective Train/Test Stratification for Object Detection</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/obj-detection-stratification/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 19:47:39 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/obj-detection-stratification/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s an unavoidable, inherent difficulty in fine-tuning deep neural networks for specific tasks, which primarily stems from the lack of training data. It would seem ridiculous to a layperson that a pretrained vision model (containing millions of parameters, trained on millions of images) could learn to solve highly specific problems. Therefore, when fine-tuned models do perform well, they seem all the more miraculous. But on the other hand, we also know that it is easier to move from the general to the specific, than the reverse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Process for Readable Code</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/code-readability-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 05:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/code-readability-process/</guid>
      <description>I took a course on data structures and algorithms over the last few months. It is being offered as a part of IIT Madras&#39; Online Degree Program in Data Science and Programming, taught by Prof Madhavan Mukund. The program is a MOOC in a true sense, with tens of thousands of students enrolling each year. The DSA course itself is offered every trimester, and sees an average of ~700 enrollments every time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: A World Without Email - Cal Newport</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/world-without-emai-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/world-without-emai-review/</guid>
      <description>This book is a good refresher on Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s central thesis which shows up in both Deep Work and Digital Minimalism, but with email as the central device. The same essential theorem, but a lot of new stories to go with it as corollaries. Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s not email technology that the book contests, but the hyperactive hive-mind that are enabled by people&amp;rsquo;s email habits.
But here&amp;rsquo;s the only thing I want to leave a note of: I was mildly annoyed by Newport&amp;rsquo;s invocation (or perhaps, misappropriation) of Claude Shannon&amp;rsquo;s information theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Travels with Charley - John Steinbeck</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/travels-with-charley-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/travels-with-charley-review/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the end of 2020, and when you&amp;rsquo;ve been stuck at home for a year, with only your dog as your constant companion, Travels with Charley is a good book to read.
But this book is a lot more about Steinbeck&amp;rsquo;s road trip than about the dog.
Steinbeck romanticises everything. If so much as a tree sheds a leaf in front of him, he bursts forth with pages of ideas, thoughts and memories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Baluta - Daya Pawar</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/baluta-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/baluta-review/</guid>
      <description>The original Marathi edition of Baluta has captivating cover art. It shows a sketch of a crow perched on the rim of an earthen pot, dropping pebbles in the pot, but completely oblivious to the glaring crack running down the pot. I remember that image from a copy lying in one corner of a bookshelf, but I was too young then to be interested. To me, this was just a sign of the artist trying to convey a sense of irony.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: City of Djinns - William Dalrymple</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/city-of-djinns-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/city-of-djinns-review/</guid>
      <description>I was first introduced to William Dalrymple in Michael Wood&amp;rsquo;s documentary, The Story of India. I watched it nearly eight years ago. The scene was shot in a Kali temple where devotees had gathered on the eve of Holi. Dalrymple is explaining what Holi means to Hindus, looking at a spot slightly off-camera. The timing of his narration is such that as soon as he finishes talking, the nearly hundred devotees in the temple throw up their hands and started dancing to chants of &amp;ldquo;Jai Mata Di&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Holi hai&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: To a God Unknown - John Steinbeck</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/to-a-god-unknown-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/to-a-god-unknown-review/</guid>
      <description>In Journal of a Novel: The East of Eden Letters, Steinbeck wrote that reading books is like driving a wedge in your life. The larger the wedge, the harder it is for parts to come together once the wedge is removed. The longer the book, the harder it is to close the mental gap around it. Steinbeck wrote this for East of Eden - his magnum opus. Surprisingly, this happens even with Steinbeck&amp;rsquo;s much shorter books.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Treasure Island - R L Stevenson</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/treasure-island-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/treasure-island-review/</guid>
      <description>There are stories you know well but you never really read well. Captain Flint (the man and the parrot), Jim Hawkins, Long John Silver and Billy Bones, the Old Sea Dog are immortal characters, without a touch of age upon them or their story. Treasure Island was perhaps the first classic I actually skimmed through many times in my childhood. I didn&amp;rsquo;t read it in earnest until now, and I did that because the final season of Black Sails is about to end.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rabies, Laziness &amp; Privilege</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/rabies-laziness-privilege/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 14:48:07 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/rabies-laziness-privilege/</guid>
      <description>It was the night of the recent 5-state assembly elections. One of my company&amp;rsquo;s clients is a major news channel, and I was at the studio late into the night, until the election commission announced that they had cancelled their press conference which was supposed to make an announcement about the final vote counts in Madhya Pradesh. A colleague offered to drop me home, and I got off at the gate of my colony, not wanting to subject my colleague to navigating the labyrinth that is any gated colony in South Delhi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weighted Loss Functions for Instance Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/weighted-loss-functions-for-instance-segmentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 14:52:19 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/weighted-loss-functions-for-instance-segmentation/</guid>
      <description>This post is a follow up to my talk, Practical Image Classification &amp;amp; Object Detection at PyData Delhi 2018. You can watch the talk here:   and see the slides here.
I spoke at length about the different kinds of problems in computer vision and how they are interpreted in deep learning architectures. I spent a fair bit of time on instance and semantic segmentation (for an introduction to these problems, watch Justin Johnson&amp;rsquo;s lecture from the Stanford CS231 course here).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: In Dubious Battle - John Steinbeck</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/in-dubious-battle-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/in-dubious-battle-review/</guid>
      <description>I have a pretty good Steinbeck collection, but this wasn&amp;rsquo;t a book I was going to read anytime soon. But I recently came across the movie adaptation and decided that other Steinbeck titles could wait. James Franco and John Steinbeck is a very attractive combination.
First of all, this book is not about communism. The eponymous battle is not a battle of the classes. It&amp;rsquo;s more of a battle men fight with themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Ask Questions After a Talk</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/how-not-to-ask-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 10:04:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/how-not-to-ask-questions/</guid>
      <description>Dedicated to the memory of Mrutyunjay Mishra (M2). He was a torrent of ideas. He encouraged me to write this post because as much as he talked endlessly without pausing to breathe, he hated wasteful discourse.
New Delhi, January 2024
 PyCon India 2017 ended last weekend in Delhi. The conference escaped the infamous winter smog-storm by a whisker. In the last few years, PyCon India has grown to become the largest PyCon outside of North America, with over a thousand participants attending from all over the country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The View from the Cheap Seats - Neil Gaiman</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/view-from-cheap-seats-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/view-from-cheap-seats-review/</guid>
      <description>I can&amp;rsquo;t think of a single fantasy character that would be Neil Gaiman. I&amp;rsquo;m tempted to think that he&amp;rsquo;s like Santa Claus, but he&amp;rsquo;s not the sort who&amp;rsquo;d care if someone was being naughty. He&amp;rsquo;s not Dumbledore or Gandalf either - he&amp;rsquo;d rather be your friend than your mentor. He&amp;rsquo;s not even the Dream of the Endless, since he&amp;rsquo;s not aware of how powerful he is.
Reading Gaiman&amp;rsquo;s nonfiction is like meditation that clears and even expands your mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing With the Konmari Method</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/playing-with-the-konmari-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 13:42:55 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/playing-with-the-konmari-method/</guid>
      <description>I heard about the bestseller The Life-Changing Magic of Tidying Up at a SciPy talk about deculttering your data science project. The speakers admitted they hadn&amp;rsquo;t read it - they were simply trying to point out that tidying up your space and tidying up your software project are both similar.
  I&amp;rsquo;ve been married and living with my wife for about a year now. After we moved into &amp;ldquo;our own home&amp;rdquo; last year, we have both undergone major role reversals when it comes to tidying up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Linearity of Bayesian Classifiers</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/linearity-bayesian-classifiers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 14:19:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/linearity-bayesian-classifiers/</guid>
      <description>In his book, Neural Networks - A Comprehensive Foundation, Simon Haykin has an entire section (3.10) dedicated to how perceptrons and Bayesian classifiers are closely related when operating in a Gaussian environment. However, it is not until the end of the section that Haykin mentions that the relation is only limited to linearity. What is interesting about this is that a Perceptron can produce the same classification &amp;ldquo;model&amp;rdquo; as a Bayesian classifier, provided that the underlying data is drawn from a Gaussian distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Geometric Proof of the Perceptron Convergence Theorem</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/perceptron-convergence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 14:45:55 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/perceptron-convergence/</guid>
      <description>The last time I studied neural networks in detail was five years ago in college. I did touch upon backpropagation when Andrew Ng&amp;rsquo;s machine learning MOOC was offered on Coursera for the first time, but beyond that I&amp;rsquo;ve only dabbled with them through keras. Then recently, when I read about Coursera&amp;rsquo;s imminent decision to pull down much of their freely available material (you can read a rant about it here), I went on a downloading spree (many thanks to the wonderful coursera-dl).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Allen Downey&#39;s Solution to the M&amp;M Problem</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/mm-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 18:33:41 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/mm-problem/</guid>
      <description>Allen Downey makes a very good case for learning advanced mathematics through programming (Check the first section of the preface of Think Bayes, titled &amp;ldquo;My theory, which is mine&amp;rdquo;). But before the reader can hit paydirt with using the Bayes theorem in programming, Downey makes you go through some elementary problems in probability, which have to be solved by hand first, if you expect to have a clear enough understanding of the concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evangelism in Foss</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/evangelism-in-foss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 19:54:09 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/evangelism-in-foss/</guid>
      <description>One of the most dangerous things that can affect any FOSS community is the tendency of evangelism for the sake of evangelism. Promoting the Python stack, expanding the userbase, etc, should come only as a consequence of the content we produce as developers. If evangelism even remotely becomes one of your goals, your quality is sure to suffer. And it&amp;rsquo;s not just the empirical evidence that prompts me to say this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organizing a Bookshelf with Multivariate Analysis</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/bookshelf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/bookshelf/</guid>
      <description>I have recently moved from Pune to Delhi. I had spent only a year in Pune, having moved there from Mumbai, where I lived for three years. Whenever I move, the bulk of my luggage consists of books and clothes. My stay in Pune was just a transition, so I never bothered to unpack and store all my stuff too carefully. Thus, a corner of my bedroom in my Pune apartment always looked like this: The actual volume of books that I carried from Pune to Delhi is about twice of what is seen in the picture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limitations of the Fourier Transform</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/fourier-limitations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2015 16:46:54 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/fourier-limitations/</guid>
      <description>My implementation of the Hilbert Huang transform (PyHHT) is quite close to a beta release. After nearly three years of inactivity, I&amp;rsquo;ve found some time to develop the PyHHT library in the last few weeks. In all this time many people have written to me about a lot of things - from the inability to use the module because of the lack of documentation, to comparison between the results of HHT and conventional time series analysis techniques.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Edge Effects in Empirical Mode Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/emd-edge-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 12:10:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/emd-edge-effects/</guid>
      <description>It has been a little over three years since I started working on a Python implementation of the Hilbert Huang Transform. When I first presented it at SciPy India 2011 (video) it was just a collection of small scripts, without packaging, testing or even docstrings. Over time PyHHT has garnered some interest, and I have, since the last few weeks, found the time to regularly work on it. I have been able to come up with a decent implementation of empirical mode decomposition, pretty much in line with everything described in the original paper by Huang et al.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
