<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Steinbeck on Jaidev&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://jaidevd.com/tags/steinbeck/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Steinbeck on Jaidev&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jaidevd.com/tags/steinbeck/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Travels with Charley - John Steinbeck</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/travels-with-charley-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/travels-with-charley-review/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the end of 2020, and when you&amp;rsquo;ve been stuck at home for a year, with only your dog as your constant companion, Travels with Charley is a good book to read.&#xA;But this book is a lot more about Steinbeck&amp;rsquo;s road trip than about the dog.&#xA;Steinbeck romanticises everything. If so much as a tree sheds a leaf in front of him, he bursts forth with pages of ideas, thoughts and memories.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: To a God Unknown - John Steinbeck</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/to-a-god-unknown-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/to-a-god-unknown-review/</guid>
      <description>In Journal of a Novel: The East of Eden Letters, Steinbeck wrote that reading books is like driving a wedge in your life. The larger the wedge, the harder it is for parts to come together once the wedge is removed. The longer the book, the harder it is to close the mental gap around it. Steinbeck wrote this for East of Eden - his magnum opus. Surprisingly, this happens even with Steinbeck&amp;rsquo;s much shorter books.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: In Dubious Battle - John Steinbeck</title>
      <link>https://jaidevd.com/posts/in-dubious-battle-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jaidevd.com/posts/in-dubious-battle-review/</guid>
      <description>I have a pretty good Steinbeck collection, but this wasn&amp;rsquo;t a book I was going to read anytime soon. But I recently came across the movie adaptation and decided that other Steinbeck titles could wait. James Franco and John Steinbeck is a very attractive combination.&#xA;First of all, this book is not about communism. The eponymous battle is not a battle of the classes. It&amp;rsquo;s more of a battle men fight with themselves.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
